this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
we talked a little bit about curvature
last time curvature these are hard
concepts they're not easy and partly
they require in order to do them in an
elegant way requires a degree of
notational notation that's a little bit
sophisticated I told you what the answer
for that I told you what the curvature
is you go around a little closed loop
and a vector doesn't quite come back to
itself and that's an indication of
curvature I've got a formula on the
blackboard I thought today I would
actually derive that formula but to do
it in anything like a reasonable amount
of blackboard space in a reasonable
amount of time it's very very useful to
introduce some I don't know if the word
is notation or conventions or
mathematical ideas that are not very
hard and in fact they're ideas that if
you've followed the development of
either my or anybody else's quantum
mechanics course you'll be extremely
familiar with so I will use those ideas
to derive the curvature the curvature as
I think somebody pointed out it was
probably Michael C you know here aren't
you Michael Michael Michael Michael yes
I think you pointed out that it's a
commutator so I think we will go through
that and show you the fast way to derive
the curvature but as I said it's
slightly abstract so we have to go
through a couple of abstract definitions
the basic idea is the idea of an
operator a linear operator operating on
a vector space but the vector space
could be a space of functions we see
that all time in quantum mechanics are
where for example the idea of a
derivative is a linear operator that
operates on functions so there's an
example another example of linear
operators are matrices
is that act on vectors but in fact we
can combine the two supposing we have a
function which is a vector well which
let's not call it a vector in a function
space that will confuse us too much
let's just call it a function supposing
we have a function but not a single
function a collection of functions which
correspond to the components of a vector
field in space
all right so depending on the
dimensionality of space if we're talking
about four-dimensional space-time that
would basically be four functions of
space and what would we call them we
might call them the Alpha of X all right
so we've already I've already mentioned
that one kind of operator an operator is
of course an operation that you can do
on a function to get another function
but a linear operator is a particular
kind of operation of which for example a
derivative with respect to any any of
the component of the components of X
derivative derivative with respect to X
mu that's an operation that can be
applied to the Alpha of X and therefore
we call it an operator that's one kind
of operator that we can have a
derivative operator let's make a list of
some operators over here first of all
there this is this by no means exhaust
all possible operators just a couple of
examples the derivative with respect to
any of the coordinates that's a linear
operator and I've connect on any kind of
function the function could be a scalar
it could be a vector if it's a vector
then of course it corresponds to
differentiating all four components of
the vector so if we play this operator
or allow it to act on the Alpha
all it really means is the derivative of
the Alpha of X with respect to X mil
that's all it means
okay hit the hit the object with the
operator and just do it all right so
derivative with respect to X is a
operator another kind of operator
doesn't differentiate it might just
multiply a function by another function
so just multiplication by any function
of X take any function of X and use it
to multiply your starting function
that's another operator that you can do
so for example applying f of X as an
operator to V alpha of X just gives you
I needn't write it over again but I will
it just gives you f of X let's click
times the alpha of X we thought is
redundant but I just want to make I just
want to distinguish between f of X as an
operator acting on the alpha of X all it
does is multiply okay so that's another
example of an operator but yet a third
kind of operator that we can do on the
alpha of X is just to multiply it by a
numerical matrix remember this V alpha
of X has components it forms a column
vector in a space for this purpose just
think of X is fixed right now just think
of X as a fixed position and we can
multiply the Alpha of X by a matrix
sorry em on V let's see what that means
M applied to the vector V means I would
like to get the Alpha component of it
well the rule for that is M alpha beta
those are the matrix entries of M
multiplying V beta and summing over beta
that gives you a vector with a component
alpha and it is a linear operation
applied to vector so there are three
examples one of them is multiplication
by a numerical matrix another is
differentiation another is multiplying
by a function of X you can even get
fancier we can take matrices alpha beta
which themselves depend on position and
multiply by V beta of X I'm not going to
write that this is equal to what I've
already written so we can have an
operator which is both the matrix and
the function of X we can even do more
complicated things in that but but I
think you get the point
now the covariant derivative the
ordinary derivative of a vector is an
operator applied to the vector but the
covariant derivative is also an operator
applied to a vector it's a more
interesting one in many respects but let
me just point that out and explain too
exactly in what sense the covariant
derivative is an operator applied to a
vector field alright we write it del M
that's that's the notation for covariant
derivative or del mu I guess I'm using
indices mu and nu and alpha and theta
this means the covariant derivative
if with respect to the coordinate X mule
so it's like D by DX mu applied to a
vector with components V alpha is by
definition or by construction the
derivative of V alpha of X with respect
to X mu plus now gamma I'm just writing
the usual expression for covariant
derivative an index down here which
don't think of that as being a matrix
index I'm going to take the matrices the
matrix indices and write them in red but
remember that the are that the
Christoffel symbol has three indices
alpha and beta now the way I want you to
think about this is for each mu there's
a matrix gamma sub mu with indices alpha
and beta so I've written the matrix
indices of course it is really just
gamma mu alpha beta but I want you to
keep in your head I want you to imagine
that gamma mu alpha beta is a set of
four matrices alpha and beta are the
matrix entries and nu just tells you
which of the four matrices you're
talking about and now you multiply that
by V beta let's use red to indicate the
matrix indices here and sum over beta
notice that that's exactly what we did
over here R except there are four such
operations one for each direction mu all
right so the covariant derivative is a
combination of differential operator
derivative operator and matrix
multiplication now gamma mu is not just
a numerical matrix typically it's a
numerical matrix that depends on
position
so it's exactly like this kind of thing
over here I we could summarize it by the
notation Delta mu equals derivative with
respect to X mu plus gamma mu now that
looks stupid what does it mean what it
means is exactly what I wrote up here
when it applies to a vector you
differentiate the vector and then you
and you add to it the matrix gamma mu
applied to the vector this gamma mu here
is a set of four matrices it's exactly
the set of four matrices over here but
I've just called it gamma mu and you
keep in mind that there are really two
hidden indices here which are acting as
matrix indices which act on the vector
so that's a little notational device
which summarizes what's written up here
but when you act on a vector to find out
what del mu does it does exactly what's
written here so that's that's a nice and
remember now that gamma mu is a function
of X
but it also has the two hidden indices
there
under four legacies time special
quarters
say it again before the season the
special importance oh yeah the moment do
it right I'm talking about force but
yesterday absolutely if we were talking
about some other space with different
dimension right yeah that's right
exactly okay so that's something to keep
in mind it's a little notational device
that we will use now I want to show you
that in the process of going around a
small closed loop and asking how
something changes when you come back to
the origin in effect
oh you're calculating a commutator of
two operators or before I do it perhaps
we should just discuss very quickly the
commute that the idea of a commutator
you mostly know what it is but I'll tell
you what it is if I have two operators
let's call them a and B whatever they
are they could have derivatives in them
they might be multiplication by matrices
they might be multiplication by matrix
functions of position that might be sums
or differences of such things a and B
the product was the product a be mean
well it means you first act with B on
whatever your operations are supposed to
act on for example if it's supposed to
act on a vector act on a vector the
result of acting with B is a new
function and then you act with a on it
so first I could be and then follow it
by it by a and that of course defines
the product they be the difference of a
B and B a is of course called the kana
tailor of a with B there's only one
little identity that I want to prove and
that we'll use and it's the following
that the commutator of a derivative
let's say the derivative with respect to
X any particular X doesn't matter the
commutator of the derivative of X with
respect I'm sorry and a function of X is
equal to and I'll play exactly what this
means in a moment DF by DX now I may or
may not have the sign right but we'll
work it out what does this mean f of X
now is just a numerical function under
not a numerical function a function but
it sort of as an operator it's not the
thing that these expressions act on the
things that the fact that they act on we
can give another name we'll just call V
of X all right it doesn't have to be a
vector function of X just some function
of X let's see what this says let's see
what the meaning of this is ah first of
all the first term is d by DX f of X
that's one term here and and the other
term is minus f of X D by DX now what's
the difference between these two well
it's hard to say with the difference
between these two are until I tell you
what they do what they do is they act on
functions of X let's say V of X V of X
now what's the meaning of this this
means first multiply by F by the time
you've multiplied by F you have a new
object in red and then differentiate the
whole thing that is the operation of
first multiplying by F and then
differentiating and it constitutes the
instruction that's associated with the
product F times D by DX over here we
first differentiate with respect to X
and then multiply by F okay let's see
what the difference is what is this DX
of F times V of X so this we just use
the product formula that the derivative
of a product is the derivative of F with
respect to x times V plus F times the
derivative of V with respect to X all
I've used is the simple calculus rule
that the derivative of a product is the
sum of well you know what then we have
to subtract off minus F DV by DX well
that's the same as this so these cancel
and what are we left with
we're left with the instruction that
when you apply the commutator of D by DX
and F this is of course a commutator of
derivative with respect to X and F on V
you get exactly the same thing as just
multiplying but V by DF by DX after all
of this whole operation including all
these derivatives the entire instruction
is to multiply V by the function DF by
DX so that's why we write that
commutator of the derivative with Lisa
and the multiplication by a function of
X is just the F by the X and what does
it mean it means when you apply this to
some V it gives you the same thing as
just multiplying by DF by DX all right
so that's a that's as tough as the
mathematics is going to get tonight I
think the idea of a commutator and the
idea of a covariant derivative as a
operator okay keep this in mind we need
we need basic little theorem but I'll
just write it out in longhand d by DX
times f of X minus f of X times D by DX
is the same thing as DF by DX try it on
any function take any function and apply
the rule here the rule here subtract
them and it's the same as multiplying by
the F by DX so we'll need that okay next
I guess we can use this one here let's
take a little rectangle I won't try to
be too general right now I'll say let's
pick two directions in space or in
space-time one direction and take a
little differential distance that I'll
call the X mu and now take another
little differential distance let's think
of it as oriented DX mu a little
infinitely small displacement think of a
displacement and now take another
displacement I'll tell you what let me
even simplify it more let me simplify it
let me simplify it more we're going to
take two displacements left it simple
enough DX the X mu this way and another
one Delta X mu this way these are two
vectors I've just indicated them with
indices mu and nu but it's not important
with the mu and nu are these are just
two distinct vectors infinitely small
both of them and they simply pick out a
pair of little elements of a of a tiny
rectangle in space or in space-time what
we're going to do is we're going to
transport parallelly transport something
around the rectangle determined by these
two vectors now let's imagine that as we
transport the object around these
vectors we're going to start at position
a we're going to go to B then we're
going to go to C we're going to go to D
and then we're going to come back to a
we're going to go right around that loop
in space but what happens
to the thing that we're transporting
around is that it won't come back to
exactly itself why because this
curvature we've seen how on the surface
of a sphere are on the surface of a cone
and when you go around the closed loop
you don't come back to yourself so I'm
going to draw next to it over here what
happens to the object the object starts
at some value which we can call V and
let's think of it as a vector V sub a I
won't draw it we'll just say it starts
at a point VA we transport it over to
here and it becomes VB we transport it
over to here and it becomes VC and then
we transport it over to here it becomes
VD but then when we transport it back
along the last leg
it doesn't quite come back to itself if
this curvature in there and so let's
just call the result V a prime let's
just call it V a prime and we're
interested in the difference between VA
and VA prime so let me show you a little
identity and then we'll interpret that
identity in terms of covariant
derivatives we're imagining
incidentally power Lily transporting
these vectors it's the effect of
curvature that makes the vector not
quite come back to itself all right so
I'll just represent that by saying we go
around in a little closed loop and we
fail to come back to the starting point
exactly not in space but in the
direction of the vector
question difficulty not magic it doesn't
come back to the same point it comes
back to the same point but comes back
oriented differently so I'm just
representing that by a little mismatch
you I don't know how else I write so let
me um let me refer take the following
identity all right
let's let's take VC minus VB okay
VC minus VB that's going to be related
to some derivative of V along this
direction here later on but for the
moment it's just VC minus VB minus V D
minus world I'm sorry I didn't do this
right I should have started differently
let me just find my notes here yeah I'm
sorry VC minus VD that's the difference
between the vector here and here and
it's clearly related to some derivative
of the vector along the direction DX mu
here along this direction which is the X
mu but let's just call it VC minus VD
for the moment and now subtract from
that minus VB minus VA e ok so let's see
what I've done I've taken VC minus VD
that's a little difference here and
subtracted the corresponding difference
down here I've taken a difference up
here and subtracted the corresponding
same thing except displaced down here
that's going to be related to a second
derivative it's a difference of
differences the C line is VD minus VB
minus VA that's the thing that makes up
a second derivative when we do it with
calculus difference of differences all
right that's one thing now I'm going to
write a similar
thing I'm going to subtract from it
let's put this in brackets and I'm going
to subtract from the whole thing a very
similar expression notice what I did
here I took a difference going
horizontally and then took the
difference of differences moving
vertically now I'm going to do it the
opposite way I'm going to take the
difference vertically and subtract off
when I move horizontally in one case I
took a derivative this way and then
differentiated it vertically now I'm
going to take a vertical derivative or
vertical difference and different and
displace it horizontally so let's see
what am i saying I'm going to subtract
the C minus VB VC minus VB and then from
that subtract the same kind of thing
over at this end except VD minus VA
prime instead of coming back to here we
know we come back to VA prime so I'm
just going to subtract VD minus VA prime
that's related to a
two different orders that we can take
differences why did you choose to
suspect the demon and C from D to a
dealer where it's okay
why do you the first term eg - three
weeks yeah and then do - VD - VA
why don't you get where did we see my
movie members from VI minus VA on the
Technodrome okay why did you choose to
do VC minus VB minus VD - VA it's the
other way round
what were we were VD - VA minus VC by VD
I know where I want to get because I
know what I want to get I know the
answer that I want to get I'm my prank
is well you'll see in a moment this has
been engineered to give me a particular
answer it's been engineered on purpose
to give me a big game yeah plus it
what's that I can define anything I want
I'm a free man
I can do anything I want I choose to
define this okay now having chose this
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
if we think of going this way is the
positive axis in this way is going the
positive axis I've always subtracted the
more positive from the less positive
point but but the point there is I've
engineered something to give me an
answer I want let's see what the answer
is
notice that VC cancels is a plus VC here
and a minus VC here okay there's a minus
VD here but a plus VD here two minuses
make a plus okay how about VB instead of
the upper and lower case B of the same
thing
is a minus VB here and a plus VB here so
many things have been engineered on
purpose to cancel out VC cancels out
here and here the D cancels out
- plus the B cancels out - plus and the
only thing that's left over is VA prime
minus VA okay VA prime minus VA equals
your right VA mark no yes you're right
VA minus VA prime nothing all right
there's two minus signs here so it's
plus VA and there's three minus signs
here so good VA minus VA prime in other
words I have succeeded in writing the
difference of VA prime and VA in terms
of various derivatives they're not yet
derivatives of course we're going to
turn them into derivatives in a minute
by making these distances infinitely
small but we've actually written the
difference in terms of a derivative of
derivatives in other words a second
derivative now let's see what that
second derivative is let's take the
first expression up on top first of all
let's take VC minus VD VC minus VD is
there is related to the derivative of V
with respect to X mu times the X mu the
derivative the V here minus V here is
the change in V when you change X mu a
little bit times the change in X so
that's the first term up here now what's
the second term the second term is
exactly the same thing except displaced
downward both of these VC minus VB and
VA is BA the C minus VD and VB minus VA
are both related to derivatives along
the axis DX mu all right
but what's the difference between them
the difference between them is a
derivative of this with respect to the
vertical axis it's the difference of
differences and so the actual full thing
that's written here are for infinitely
small for infinitesimally
is we differentiate this again the V
it's actually excuse me I'm not writing
it correctly this should be covariant
derivative because we're parallelly
transporting because we're not just
doing ordinary derivatives we're
parallelly transporting and taking the
covariant derivative the covariant
difference between these so the
covariant difference between these is
covariant derivative of the x DX mu and
then if we want to subtract off the
second half of it here we simply have to
multiply it by we have to do another
derivative del with respect to X nu and
then which way is it
it is DX mu delta X nu that's what
appears here the derivatives or the
difference of derivative differences the
difference when you transport along the
x axis and then take the difference of
that when you transport the whole thing
along the Delta x axis okay so that's
what this is what about the other term
the second term that we subtracted off
here it's exactly the same thing except
in the opposite order where instead of
well let's just look at it what's the
first thing here we're subtracting this
is VC minus VB
VC minus VB is the derivative with
respect to the vertical axis so that's
del nu V times Delta X nu oops times I
get it right yes times Delta X no and
then the MU times the X mu in other
words the difference between these is
just the order in which I differentiate
if I I can differentiate in a horizontal
direction or I can differentiate in the
vertical direction covariant derivatives
the difference between those two
derivatives constitutes what I've
written here so what do we found we
found that the change in V when you go
around a closed loop
first of all contains these little
differential elements the X mu and Delta
X nu that's the little area element
that's the little area element contained
in the in the rectangle rectangle or
parallelogram doesn't have to be a
rectangle could be a parallelogram and
then it contains Delta Nu Delta mu V
minus Delta mu delta nu V what is that
that's the commutator of Delta Nu with
Delta mu on V first term Delta Nu is to
the left Delta mu is to the right and
the second term Delta mu is to the left
Delta Nu to the right so here's a fancy
expression involving the commutator of
two covariant derivatives the commutator
of two covariant derivatives
each one is itself an operator when you
commute them you get another operator
when you apply that commutator to the
original vector starting vector V and
multiplied by Delta by these deltas it
gives you the change in V in going
around the small loop so it's a very
concise trick to compute how a vector
changes when you go around a small
infinitesimal loop which is made up out
of a pair of vectors Delta and D Delta X
and DX okay quite an elegant expression
and now all we have to do is plug in the
definition of the covariant derivatives
work out the commutator and what is the
object that we will have constructed
incidentally the curvature tensor
because it's the curvature tensor that
tells you what happens when you go
around a little loop okay so let's write
them down we're interested let's write
out the expression yeah
okay so let's writing it out explicitly
it's D nu plus gamma nu that's del mu P
I'll bring you over to here again del mu
is just derivative plus multiplication
by gamma and remember gamma is a matrix
or a set of matrices d nu plus gamma nu
that's Delta that's Delta Nu and then
the MU plus gamma mu that's the product
Delta Nu on the delta nu on the left and
Delta mu on the right now we have to
switch them and subtract minus the MU
plus gamma mu times the nu plus gamma nu
and then multiply it by the vector V but
for the moment I'm only interested in
writing the operators down
okay so let's work it out the first term
that I get contains no gammas it's just
Delta Nu times Delta mu minus Delta mu
oh sorry not Delta it's just derivative
with respect to X nu derivative with
respect to X mu minus derivative with
respect to X mu derivative with respect
to X note is everybody comfortable with
my writing expressions like derivative
with respect to X nu is just D mu okay I
think I've done that before but these
sub mu just means derivative with
respect to X mu all right so the first
term is just gotten by d nu times D mu
sorry D Delta derivative derivative new
derivative mu minus derivative mu
derivative no what is this that's zero
ordinary derivatives commute with each
other ordinary derivatives it doesn't
matter the order of differentiation so
the first term is zero okay the term
just involving derivatives next
we get gamma nu times D mu but then we
have another one over here which is
almost identical except in the opposite
order D mu times gamma nu so that's
minus d nu sorry D mu times gamma nu
okay D nu no yes no no yes gamma nu
times D mu that's here and then D mu
gamma nu that's here what is this this
is just a commutator of gamma mu with D
mu we can write this as I guess it's
minus the commutator of D nu with gamma
nu gamma nu is a function of X D nu is
just derivative what is this commutator
okay now you have to go back and
remember yeah
there it is there it is derivative times
F minus F times derivative that's
exactly what we have here and I hope I
have a sign like this should then be
minus the derivative of gamma nu with
respect to X mu that's just a function
but it's the function that's made by
differentiating gamma okay that's the I
get that term let's see which ones are
by taking care of let's we've taken care
of this product and that product now
we've gotten gamma nu times D mu that's
this and the MU times gamma nu now
there's another term in here alright
let's collect this term there's another
term in which mu and nu are interchanged
and which mu and nu are interchanged and
it comes in with the opposite sign that
one is going to be plus d nu gamma mu
and that's equal to plus D by DX nu
gamma mu you can hunt around in here for
those terms one of them is easy to find
let's see
derivative with respect to here it is
derivative with respect to X mu x no
derivative with respect to X nu that's
here times gamma mu that's this one
comes in with the opposite sign ah looks
the same except mu and or interchange
then you have the opposite sign okay yes
GUI what is that I mean that's a matrix
right it is a matrix so what's its
derivative with respect to X but a
matrix which depends on position so it
means you differentiate each component
of the matrix yeah yeah it just means
you go through the matrix
differentiating its components right
okay so that's easy and just please keep
in mind that there are matrix entries
here which I've which I've purged that
of the formulas and now what's the last
term the last term is gamma nu times
gamma mu minus gamma mu times gamma nu
so the last term I'll write it in here
is plus gamma mu gamma mu minus gamma mu
gamma nu
now why isn't that zero why isn't gamma
nu x gamma mu equal minus gamma mu gamma
mu equal to 0 because the matrices right
okay so let's collect it all together
and put back the matrix indices and we
will have an expression for the
curvature we'll have an expression for
the small change when you go around the
closed loop
so let's see we first have D nu gamma mu
I'll put in the indices in a minute I
just want to write it out minus D mu
gamma nu plus gamma nu gamma mu minus
gamma mu gamma nu okay let's put back
the matrix entries now I'll do that red
Oh
alpha beta alpha beta but here we have
matrix multiplication we want the alpha
beta 'the element of the matrix gamma
times gamma so that becomes Alpha Delta
Delta beta that's multiplying the matrix
gamma Alpha Delta by the matrix gamma
Delta beta Einstein summation convention
sum over Delta that's a simple way to do
matrix multiplication the same thing
over here Alpha Delta Delta beta that's
the and what's the whole thing the whole
thing is the curvature tensor but what
do we do with it what we do with it is
we multiply it first of all we multiply
it by Delta X nu and DX mu
delta-x new the XML that's a little
rectangle or the sides of our little
rectangle and then we multiply it by V
beta and what does it give us it gives
us the change in V alpha the only open
index here is alpha I hope new and mu
have been soaked up alpha beta yeah it
gives us the change in V alpha when we
go around the closed loop while we
change is a very small change if you go
around the small loop or drawing it as a
big change but that's the change and
notice that it contains the edge sizes
quadratically so it's proportional to
some area in there
it contains V itself so it's some
operator acting on V and it contains
this big structure this big ugly
structure here called the Riemann tensor
I'm sorry yep
right
all right this is the Riemann tensor our
new mu alpha beta and I think in my
notes last time I may have had an
indexer misplaced
that's the Riemann tensor and it is d nu
gamma mu alpha beta - oh yeah
okay I'm gonna I'm going to do it this
way plus gamma nu alpha delta gamma mu
delta beta - what happens is if you went
to change mu and nu I'm not going to
write the whole thing out it contains
one term with a mu and mu and the other
term is identical except just
interchange knowing mu not surprising
since after all we were taking a
commutator of something that we get that
we get minus signs in it that's the
Riemann tensor and we could plug it into
this formula over here and we see that
the Riemann tensor is the construction
for telling you how to change a vector
when you go around a little closed loop
perfect
kind of say it looks like a picnic on a
plane I picked the plane I pick the
plane to go around so it doesn't matter
I got a choice
Yeah right once I know the general
formula I can choose that plane anyway I
like by choosing Delta X nu + Delta X nu
to be arbitrary little vectors in other
words any plane that can be
characterized by - two vectors any two
vectors characterize a plane so if I
choose two vectors - infinitesimal
vectors Delta X nu and DX mu these are
two different vectors Delta and D then
they define a plane and that's right
what we're doing is we're picking out a
plane taking a small little loop in that
plane going around that small little
loop and seeing what happens when we
covariantly transport a vector and the
result is that when you go around it
will reorient itself actually
that question was our question is is
that you and new are three indices so
that really is oh yes
yep take it not they're not free indices
in this final formula here before I
contract them with this little area
element they're free indices but when I
decide what yeah
machine that you can you get to say
Piedmont tensor no matter what plane yes
you know the same we won thanks refused
any components of it when you choose
different plays right
and what happens on Delta X and X dot X
nu DX mu go to zero what else goes to
zero to get me one zero in length for
example yeah the change in the vector
goes to zero the change in the vector if
you go around the small loop as the loop
gets smaller and smaller let's say we
take this vector and we go around the
smaller we make this loop the smaller
the difference between the vector when
we go around but we want to keep track
of that small distance it's that small
difference we could for example choose a
bigger circle and integrate up the
effects of a small little bits of
curvature we want to keep track
difference nothing to make our attention
post me like depends on the size of that
show nothing the Riemann picks it
depends on it this is what the tango
yeah this does okay
hmmm something else to go 2-0 the answer
goes to zero okay let me change what I
was yeah what's up I can see what you
might kind of confused let's put this up
here equals Delta the the notice this
quantity is a quadratic in small
deviations so it's doubly small so we're
adding up all the curvature components
of each of the planes right to the bases
back supposing I chose supposing I
arbitrarily said let's take Delta X
newgy at the line along the x axis I'm
just saying because we're contracting
those yes adding up components in all of
the different directions right that's
right okay so that's the Riemann tensor
if you now use now I don't know any well
I know some simple ways to see some of
the symmetries of this incidentally it
is a tensor it's made up out of
covariant derivatives of covariant
derivatives and covariant derivatives
are the things which make tensors so it
is guaranteed to be a tensor
since it's a tensor I can lower the
index alpha if I like and put all the
indices downstairs I can do that if I
like ah and we just lower the index how
do we lower indices yeah yeah by
multiplying by the metric of the
appropriate way and so we can also write
our new mu alpha beta it's a different
thing as different different values but
we can get it directly from here all
right it has anti-symmetric indices mu
and mu it's clearly anti-symmetric under
nu mu interchange if you interchange mu
and mu you want to change sorry we need
to change the term from here with a term
from here
so it's anti-symmetric if you
interchange nu and mu keeping alpha and
beta fixed it also happens to be
anti-symmetric this is something you can
check by direct calculation it's also
anti-symmetric if you interchange alpha
and beta you can prove this in a number
of ways which i'm not going to do but
one of the ways is by simply demanding
that the vector as its transported
around doesn't change its length that's
enough to prove that it's anti-symmetric
with alpha and beta i'm not going to
prove that we've done as much
mathematics as i want to do tonight so
let me just indicate that by putting a
little arrow here and a minus sign that
means that if you interchange mu and nu
the sign of the Riemann tensor changes
it's also anti-symmetric with respect to
alpha and beta and it has the further
property that if I literally pick up mu
and nu and interchange them without fuh
and beta its symmetric so I'll indicate
that by by some sort of plus sign like
that what this would what this plus sign
means is that this is the same or it's
equal to our alpha beta mu nu no nu mu
nu mu if I take alpha and beta and
interchange them with nu and mu the pair
of them then nothing changes if I
interchange a new and a mule without
changing an alpha and beta it changes
sign and if I interchange an alpha and
beta without interchanging mu and nu it
changes sign so those are the basic
properties of the Riemann tensor
probably
probably i'm almost undoubtedly
everything you want to know about it
there oh you can find out by plugging in
for the gammas their expression in terms
of derivatives of the g's so let's see
what it is okay let's just get a rough
idea what kind of things does a gamma
have in it the gammas have in them first
derivatives of the metric has inverse
matrix inverse metrics but it contains
as far as derivatives go each gamma has
is proportional to a single derivative
of a G I'll write them out later but
there let's just keep in mind that means
that these terms here contain second
derivatives of G so the ars have second
derivatives with of G of the metric and
these terms here are quadratic in first
derivatives the gamma contains a first
derivative a gamma times another gamma
contains a first derivative times
another first derivative so the RS
contain two kinds of terms one of them
being quadratic and first derivatives
and the other kind being second
derivative of a G second derivatives of
G and quadratic and first derivatives of
G they always contain two derivatives
sometimes the two derivatives act on one
G giving you second derivatives
sometimes it'll be a product of a
derivative of G times another derivative
of G and that's the character of the
Riemann tensor it is quadratic and
derivatives made up out of the
Christoffel symbols Christoffel symbols
are themselves made up out of the metric
so if you know the metric tensor is a
function of position with a great deal
of labor and effort you can work out or
I think it's twenty four components
independent components of the Riemann
tensor
it's only six and three dimensions one
to two directions yeah skip spoiling for
you to divide both sides in a long line
by DX mu DX me would get a mixed partial
on the right hand side yeah I think this
is the way to express it I know you're
waiting for me to do that but I don't
think it's appropriate to do it it's not
a second derivative anything it is what
it is all right once now as I said the
basic idea is simple enough the
equations are rather complicated and not
terribly pretty they can be simplified I
don't I don't think I have a rote we can
also write in a very simple form we can
just write that are nu nu alpha beta
thought of the matrix are thought of as
a matrix so let's suppress its matrix
indices is just the commutator of two
covariant derivatives nu and mu that's
the most elegant way to write the
Riemann tensor and to remember that each
one of the objects in there is itself a
matrix whatever I alpha beta
that's an elegant representation for it
but when you actually come to calculate
this is the thing that you are
calculating when you calculate the
Riemann tensor now there are some other
tensors that you can make up out of the
Riemann tensor the Ricci tensor and the
cur and the scalar curvature I'll define
them now they play a very important role
in general relativity know this is the
thing with four indices but I've
suppressed two of the indices and it's
anti-symmetric on the mu and nu okay so
it's definitely not the the Ricci tensor
the Ricci tensor now I could try
contracting well let's see what we can
do let's see what we can make up
let's take our mu nu alpha beta in fact
let's hit yeah let's take it in that
form can i contract mu with noon how
would I do that I would multiply it by G
mu nu and that would give me a thing
with just an alpha beta index this is
zero does anybody know why this is 0
because R is anti-symmetric
and G is symmetric whenever you take a
symmetric matrix and contract it with an
anti-symmetric matrix you'll always get
zero you get as many positive terms as
negative terms and so you'll always get
zero so you can't contract the meua nu
and get anything interesting same thing
with the alpha beta remember that this
matrix is also when everybody is written
with lower indices it's also
anti-symmetric with respect to alpha and
beta so contracting alpha and beta will
also lead the grief you'll get nothing
but if you contract alpha with nu for
example meaning to say you multiply the
whole thing well what does it mean it
means doesn't mean it means you just
write R mu alpha alpha beta and contract
and sum over the alphas that gives you a
nonzero thing which is called the Ricci
tensor and it's R mu beta all right it
exists it's not 0 and how many
components that it's also symmetric the
reason it's symmetric is one of the some
of the symmetries of the Riemann tensor
it's not hard to show you know enough
I've told you enough to prove that it's
symmetric when you went to change mu and
beta that is where is it if I bring this
alpha downstairs alpha beta then it's
the symmetry on the interchanging these
two the result is that our mu beta is
symmetric it's equal to our beta mu
this one and that one
there's no ambiguity really apart from a
sign if you choose the wrong two to
contract you'll get zero by antisymmetry
if you pick the right one they're all
the same there's enough symmetry to make
sure the answer is always the same well
if I put the alpha if I put the let's
see if I chronica there yeah yeah that's
right or we could put the Alpha Index
downstairs and then just multiplied by G
new alpha in other words we've got to
contract these two indices mu and alpha
we can do it in any number of ways all
the same thing and you get a tensor with
two indices take any tensor with foreign
disease and by contracting the indices
identifying an upper with a lower and
then summing you remove those two
indices and you get something with to
fewer indices so that's our beta mu and
that's Ricci
this is Riemann
okay there's one last tensor that you
can make in the last century on some way
to differentiate the two different bars
right
Ricci le monde yeah you have to put a
number of indices yeah they're both
called are unfortunately and then
there's one more thing that's called are
it's the Ricci scalar the Ricci scalar
is just gotten by taking sorry or they
are the curvature scalar sorry the
curvature scalar is just gotten by
taking the Ricci tensor and contracting
its two indices which you do by writing
our beta mu G beta mu and that's just
called R and it's just called the
curvature scalar if the curvature scalar
is not zero the space is curved but if
the curvature scalar is zero it doesn't
mean that the space is not curved any
one of the any component of the
curvature if it's not zero the space is
not flat but you can have situations
where the curvature scalar is zero even
though the components of either the
Ricci or the Riemann tensor are not so
the vanishing well okay let's limit let
me put it this way the vanishing of the
of the curvature scalar is necessary for
a space to be flat but it's not when I
say vanishing I mean vanishing
everywhere I mean vanishing as a
function if it vanishes that doesn't
mean the space is flat but if it doesn't
vanish it means the space that I say
this right it is necessary for flatness
but not sufficient except in two
dimensions in two dimensions there is
only one independent component or
of the Riemann tensor easy to prove and
it can be rewritten in terms of the
scalar curvature so in two dimensions
it's both necessary and sufficient for a
space to be flat for the Riemann or for
the curvature scalar to be everywhere
zero yahood example that'd be a saddle
point a seven-point saddle Robin oh you
were nothing zero not scared let's care
what that is here no no it's good okay
in three dimensions it's necessary and
sufficient for the Ricci tensor to be
zero in order to have a flat space-time
but in higher than three dimensions
neither the scalar nor the Ricci tensor
by itself completely determine whether
the space is flat in principle you have
to check every single one of the
independent components of the Riemann
tensor to determine whether its base is
flat but if all the components of the
Riemann tensor are everywhere zero the
space is flat
now I haven't proved that but that is a
theorem that is a theorem a great circle
I'm scared
that's only remember the Riemann
curvature any of these curvatures has to
do with smaller loops what happens when
you go around small little loops in
other words the statement is if the
Riemann tensor is at the exit scalar
curvature is zero then any little loop
that you go around that you'll come back
and so I think it is confusing with the
Judas Judas it
actually if you were around a Bartok
circle that is not a gdz no no
definitely not
that's right if you go around the Arctic
Circle at ten degrees around the Arctic
Circle that is not a geodesic I'm not
sure if that's what the confusion was or
not that is not that is not a geodesic
it's great circles which are geodesics
okay so now we know a great deal about
what curvature is keep in mind that
curvature does not have to do with the
way the thing is embedded in space I
mean for example this piece of paper has
zero curvature whether you do this to it
that to it this to it that to it or any
other kind of bending that you can do to
it the intrinsic properties of the space
the properties that are felt by that
tiny little bug that can only walk on
the space and can only feel his way
around on the space itself those
properties don't depend on the way that
it's embedded in a higher dimensional
space the properties the properties of
how its embedded are called extrinsic
properties so if I press this down on
here it has zero intrinsic curvature
it also has zero extrinsic curvature if
I bend it up like that
it now has zero intrinsic curvature but
nonzero extrinsic curvature so don't
confuse those two concepts and at the
moment we're only interested in
intrinsic properties of the space what
we can feel moving in our own space-time
okay so that I think is curvature now I
want to come to motion of particles slow
particles in particular what we want to
do I'll tell you right now the the the
Riemann tensor of course and its various
friends here are the gravitational field
and we're going to want to find the
approximate connection between these
things and the easier to think about
Newtonian approximation how are these
objects connected to the things that
Newton would have understood as the
gravitational field
I don't think Newton ever really defined
the field concept but he we could have
easily explained it to him as the field
of acceleration as we move around in
space with a point mass and see what its
acceleration is that acceleration
defines a vector field every point in
space and that's what we would call the
gravitational field and the question is
how is it connected there is much much
more complicated objects here all right
to the first step is to understand
acceleration along geodesics what the
idea of acceleration along geodesics now
geodesic is the straightest possible
path the straightest possible path in
space-time if there's no curvature is of
course a straight line straight line
means unaccelerated uniform motion no
acceleration but in curved spacetime is
just no not no concept which is quite
equivalent to a perfect straight line
and no matter what we do we will find
the concept of acceleration in a curved
space-time and that's what is gets
related to the Newton force law okay but
let's go back now I think we did a bit
of this last time but I
go through it more carefully now I want
to talk only now about things which are
moving slowly we're going to restrict
ourselves for a little bit two things
which are moving slowly and furthermore
they're moving slowly in a gravitational
field which is not so strong that the
Newtonian approximation breaks down can
you think of a gravitational field where
the Newtonian approximation really
breaks down badly sure a black hole or
the expansion of the universe or
whatever so if we're thinking about the
kinds of gravitational fields which are
made up out of planets and stars and so
forth for which the Newtonian
approximation is good then general
relativity should reduce to Newtonian
physics we should have an F equals MA
and we should have a force law which we
recognize as Newton
so let's first begin with the F equals
MA idea and let's just think about the
acceleration of a particle moving on a
geodesic the role of general relativity
is very simple particles move along
geodesics
in space-time it's a marvelously simple
rule a lot simpler than anything Newton
could have said they just go as straight
ahead as they can in space-time what's
the equation for that here's the
equation for a DA geodesic
it's just that the tangent vector is
covariantly constant along the
trajectory is just the second X by D tau
squared X mu tau is proper time along
the trajectory D tau squared is equal to
G mu nu DX mu DX no that's the tau
squared take a square root and it
becomes D tau that's a longer trajectory
and the second derivative of X with
respect to tau squared plus gamma gamma
let's see what I have here Sigma lambda
mu D X Sigma by D tau the X lambda by D
tau this is the covariant derivative of
the tangent vector remember what the
tangent vector is the tangent vector is
the vector whose components are DX mu by
D tau that's the tangent vector all
right then we take the tangent vector
and covariantly differentiate it along
the trajectory itself if this is equal
to zero everywhere is along the
trajectory then the trajectory is a
geodesic or another way of saying it is
this becomes the equation of motion for
a particle moving in a gravitational
field or moving in a spacetime metric
all right now let's imagine a frame of
reference let's suppose is a frame of
reference in which everything that we're
interested in is moving slowly by
comparison with the speed of light and
everything is changing in time slowly
nothing is very very rapidly changing in
time that's the condition for Newton to
be approximately correct all right first
of all what's the connection if a
trajectory is moving slowly that means
in some frame of reference it's moving
practically vertically what is the
connection then I oh we're going to make
a jump what's the connection then
between tau along the trajectory and
ordinary time yeah okay there's an
assumption involved there and I'll tell
you what the assumption is the
assumption that's involved is that G mu
nu is almost equal to Delta mu nu or
sorry is almost
equal to a dumb you new remember what a
dumb you new is it's the metric of
special relativity right so there are
two assumptions one is that there is a
frame of reference in which everything
is moving slowly and everything is
changing slowly and will work in that
frame of reference and the other is that
the gravitational field is weak to say
that the gravitational field is weak is
to say that G mu nu is equal to 8 mu nu
plus a small correction that the
correction the flat space-time is small
ok let's make that assumption
now with that assumption things moving
slowly and the metric approximately of
the Minkowski kind then it is true that
X naught which can also be called T is
the same as tau along a trajectory again
I've set C equal to 1 so so you can put
back the C's they're worth putting back
but that in particular says that the X
naught by D tau is equal to 1 plus tiny
tiny Corrections Corrections which are
small when things are moving slowly with
us compared to the speed of light and if
the X by D tau is always equal to 1 if
the x naught by D tau is always equal to
then the second derivative of x naught
with respect how squared is always going
to be very small so we don't have to
worry about that that's that's not
something we have to worry about the the
time component of X it's the space
components of X that we want to deal
with all right so once we say the tau is
close to t2 with in very small
quantities we could pick out one spatial
component of X which one should we pick
out let's just pick out X X itself as a
X as an x y&z
let's pick out X these second X by D tau
squared is the same as D second X by DT
squared also known as the X component of
acceleration alright so the first thing
is in a frame in which everything is
moving slowly and in which the
gravitational field is practically small
small means close to the the standard
Minkowski metric in that case this term
in the equation is nothing but ordinary
acceleration in this case along the x
axis a similar one for y and z plus now
what appears here since this is
acceleration what appears here must be
associated with gravitational force we
might want to multiply by M but we don't
let's let's not bother here's the
acceleration and so it's related by a
factor of M to the force but let's look
at it for a minute the X by D tau if we
pick out a space component of X the X by
D tau is small very small why is it
small because by assumption we're
working in a frame of reference where
everybody is moving very slowly moving
slowly means the X by D tau is small the
Y by D tau small and the Z by D tau is
small the only components of the four
velocity which are large there's only
one component of the four velocity which
is large and that's the X naught by D
tau how big is the X naught by D tau one
so to a good approximation the only
thing which is here is gamma zero zero
mu DX not by D tau but that's just one
the X naught by D tau there is no mu
yeah yeah yeah good oh yeah I was just
about to do that right yeah anyway these
are 1 and now this is just X or 1
depending on how you like your notation
X is the first component of x y&z so
this can either be 1 or X so what do we
found out we found out that apart from a
minus sign equals minus that this is the
field of acceleration the Christoffel
symbol but a particular the coastal
symbol with two zeros downstairs and an
X upstairs is the X component of
acceleration with a minus sign in there
let's write that out let's write it out
taking into account some approximations
first of all what is this gamma X 0 0
we're going to assume now that G mu nu
is equal to 8 mu nu plus small
correction that also means that G super
mu nu is 8 a super mu nu which is the
same - the same symbol plus small
Corrections okay so let's write out what
this gamma symbol is it's equal to G X X
with upstairs X's
1/2 times the derivative of G x0 with
respect to X naught plus the derivative
of G x0 X with respect to X naught minus
the derivative of G north-north with
respect to X right that's basically what
it is what I'm doing is I'm using for G
out here just a de why don't I keep the
corrections the small curve alright I'm
not going to keep the small Corrections
to G in this expression out here why not
because it's second-order obviously this
is proportional to the corrections if
there are small Corrections this will be
proportional to the corrections why
because when you differentiate G you get
nothing from the big term in G and you
only get contributions from the small
term so this here is already first-order
in small things all right if I want to
keep only things which are first-order
in small things I don't want to write
the corrections to G here this just
becomes a this just becomes a 2x X and
what is a 2x X the X X component you
fail who was it you get a D what is a 2
X X minus 1
remember it's DT squared minus DX
squared right so we got to keep our
signs correct I'm going to lose the sign
I'm sure I'll lose the sign let's see
this is since I've got a minus here I
probably want them another minus here
but a the xxxx is - I know that my sign
is going to come out use Islam because
you're going to get a GPT over there so
yeah no it doesn't in that sense it
doesn't matter uh well no let's just
flip the careful and be consistent aina
X X is minus one so let's see I've lost
now I've lost the thread I don't
remember how many times I've changed my
sign from the original equation yeah
so that's this minus sign minus sign for
the first opposite there's a leading
minus sign there from the either - you
have no idea what I have oh yeah yeah
but this is - you get 38 you got the
third term and to those terms right
right right now the reason that these go
away why do these go away these go away
because we're assuming that everything
is moving slowly if everything Maurice
is moving slowly
it means the components of the
gravitational field change slowly if the
sources of the gravitational field are
moving slowly for example the Sun is at
rest in summer in our frame if the Sun
is at rest in our frame then the
components of the metric don't change
with time none of the components of the
metric will change rapidly with time if
everything is moving very slowly so in
the Newtonian approximation the time
dependence here is very small and we can
neglect this the only big term is this
one and so all together then we get an
equation that the second derivative of X
with respect to T squared is equal to
1/2 with a minus sign it looks like to
me the derivative of Jean
what not with respect to X what would
your written in it in Newtonian in
Newtonian gravity let's go back to the
Tony arrival now you would have written
gm1 well let's not that's not worry
about the detailed form of the
gravitational field but yeah yeah the
force is a gradient or the acceleration
is the gradient of the potential of the
potential right so we will have written
in Newtonian physics the second
derivative of X with respect to T
squared is equal to minus I think the
derivative of the potential let's call a
Phi with respect to X and basically the
same kind of formula
I have a feeling I have a saw Diablos
yeah
but I've dropped the sorry TSSs negative
what a negative sign
we're rich we're going to tough
assignment it's just super sweet
princess gamma 0 0 XE just point out
there's this big G X X there I have a
feeling I've lost assignment let me just
see yeah I thought I kept track of it
but now it looks now it looks
I'm it's too late and I'm too tired to
go through the signs carefully so well
at of course it is important but at this
point at this point is not so important
it is important but will quill will come
will have to come back to it I'll get
the Sun it's either right or it's wrong
I have a 50% chance of of gravity being
attractive or repulsive that's the point
okay
get the wrong sign there and you'll find
the gravity is repulsive instead of
attractive alright so it appears then
that to within a sign there is a close
connection between the gravitational
potential and G naught naught now I
thought that alright the way it's
written it says the G naught naught in
this approximation should be equal to
Phi but does it say that not quite
why not plus a constant right plus a
constant plus a constant
and a factor of two good the factor of
two goes over here yeah so G naught
naught the time time component of the
metric incidentally very far from a
gravitating object the metric should
just go over to the standard Minkowski
form without any gravity in that case
the C would just be one we'll come back
to it we'll come back to what this
constant is it's really just one but we
will come back to it okay so in some way
G naught naught is created as related to
twice the gravitational potential keep
that in mind we're not going to not
going to write down today the theory of
a concentrated mass but that will come
up we've now learned something about the
metric tensor we've learned that if we
know what the Newtonian potential is
then we have an approximation to a piece
of the the metric tensor that's
information and it's information that
we'll use in trying to build the the
Einstein theory okay now let's keep
let's keep that in mind and let's go
back to Newton or let's continue with
Newton and say what do we know about
this quantity Phi well Phi is the thing
whose gradient is the field of
acceleration when I curl earlier in the
course what I called a the acceleration
field is minus or plus and now I've lost
track again I'm going to have trouble
with sines tonight I think it's just the
derivative of Phi that's futz like force
is minus the derivative of Phi with
respect to X I think that's right
ah definition alright now what how is
Phi connected to the sources of the
gravitational field here's well going
now we know that Phi is connected to the
metric in a certain way which I've
raised up out of sight Phi is connected
to the metric or is essentially a piece
of the metric on the other hand Phi is
related to the sources of the
gravitational field which are mass well
that's going to tell us that the metric
itself is somehow controlled by masses
so what's the connection between Phi and
mass density let's call mass density Rho
Rho is mass per unit volume okay let me
remind you that the connection between a
and Rho is that the divergence of a is
equal to now is that correct no there's
a factor of G what else 4pi and a minus
sign if i'm not mistaken right now this
tells us since a is the gradient of phi
and this is the divergence of a this can
be written as del squared Phi or maybe
with a minus sign is equal to 4 pi Rho G
where del square root of Phi means the
second derivative of Phi with respect to
X plus the second derivative of Phi with
respect to y plus the second derivative
of Phi with respect to Z equals del
squared Phi so here we have an equation
which is some simplified approximation
to an equation which which connects the
metric to the mass density now mass
density of course is the same as energy
density equals MC squared and C is equal
to 1 in our units and so the right hand
side is really 4 pi G times the energy
density well the last time we talked
about energy density and momentum
density and we gave it we put them
together into a big matrix and the
matrix was called the energy momentum
tensor ok T naught naught what was T
naught naught energy density what was T
naught one energy flux or energy flow
how about T one not momentum density all
right on the right hand side it's pretty
clear that what we have is T naught
naught the energy density which is the
same as the mass density so we have an
equation which has the form del squared
Phi is 4 pi G times T naught naught
roughly speaking but what is on the
left-hand side on the left-hand side is
the second derivative of Phi which is
closely related to the second derivative
of G naught not remember what was the
connection now Phi is equal to either
one-half G naught naught a place do you
know it not which way was it Phi is
equal to one-half G naught not so on the
left hand side I can write that this is
one-half del squared second derivative
of G naught naught these are spatial
derivatives two spatial derivatives
Gino or not and that's equal to 4pi I'm
going to write 8 pi GT not not and get
rid of the half here okay we're starting
to get some geometric picture of how
gravity works that the energy momentum
tensor it's not not component somehow
determines G naught naught but what's
wrong with this equation is this a
sensible equation well it's an OK
equation but the problem with it is that
it's not a tensor equation it's not
written explicitly as a tensor equation
it's not clear that we've derived it in
a particular frame of reference a frame
of reference where everything is moving
slowly unless we can express it as a
tensor equation we will not expect it to
be true in an arbitrary frame of
reference the whole point of tensors is
to write equations which are the same in
every reference frame and while the
right hand side is indeed a component of
a tensor tensor equations incidentally
mean whole tensors all that components
are equal to other tensors not just that
the north-north component of a tensor is
equal to some other north-north
component first of all I don't like this
because it has two indices downstairs
and one index up stand two indices
upstairs that that's really not the
problem with this we could lower both
these indices and not worry about that
but the problem is it's just not a
tensor equation as it stands is there a
tensor equation which in the limit that
we're talking about everything moving
slowly weak gravitational fields is
there a tensor equation which becomes
equal to this well on the right hand
side we have a piece of a tensor we
should be looking for some kind of
equation which looks something like this
a tensor on the left-hand side made up
only out of the components of the metric
let's give it a name let's call it G mu
nu I don't know what it is yet I know
some things about it but I don't know
what it is yet but it's something made
up only out of the metric and some of
its derivatives and on the right hand
side 8 pi G T mu nu supposing I was able
to find a tensor which had the property
that in the frame where everything is
moving slowly it's not not component
simply reduced to this then my guess
would be that the full gravitational
theory in frames of reference of
reference or are in situations where
things are varying rapidly in situations
where the approximations are not quite
so good this would become the full
theory so the question is what is this
well let's see what it has it's made up
out of the metric and it's made up out
of second derivatives of the metric what
tensors oh and it also has to be a
pencil with only two indices why two
indices because it's going to be equal
to some tensor on the right hand side
with two indices the energy density is a
piece of a tensor with two indices the
left hand side has to have two indices
made up only out of the metric and only
having second derivatives or being
containing second derivatives of the
metric and suggestions by now Bowa might
go there yeah arm you know but there's
another tensor that we can make with two
indices that also is made up out of the
same kind of things and I'll tell you
what it is yeah are the scalar R times G
mu nu
a scaler remember that stuff this is the
this curvature scalar the scalar
curvature everybody's been contracted
times the metric itself so there are two
tensors which could go here and some
combination of them some coefficient
let's call it a a numerical coefficient
the my numerical now I mean like it
could be 3 or it could be 1 or it could
be 7 or whatever plus some other
numerical coefficient B times Delta mu
nu times R and that's it there are no
other tensors which contain only the
second second derivatives and which are
made up only out of the metric other
than a times R mu nu plus B times Delta
mu nu R that's equal to 8 pi G times
team you know so cop gym you know sorry
gym you know
right left hand side is a tensor the
right hand side is a tensor if they're
the same in one frame they're the same
in all frames so all we have to do is
search for some numerical coefficients a
and B so that the left hand side in the
limit of everybody moving slowly is just
del squared of G not not we're not going
to do that tonight there is a solution
to that if there wasn't we wouldn't be
here
it's called capital G mu nu that's also
called the Einstein tensor all right but
that's the goal so the logic has been
pretty clear we've we've decided to look
at the theory in in frames of reference
where everything is recognizably small
in Newtonian came to the conclusion that
our equations are going to be something
like this how did we find out that G mu
nu was all the G naught naught was
related to the gravitational potential
by studying the theory of geodesics all
right by studying the theory of
geodesics we found that G naught naught
was essentially the same as Phi with a
factor of 2 well they are derivatives of
G naught naught are the same as
derivatives of Phi and this equation
represents nothing but del squared Phi
is 4 pi 0 and then look for a
generalization of this which has the
form of a tensor equation so far I
haven't told you what is here but it's
more or less obvious that it should have
something to do with the curvature
tensor simply because it's got to be
made up out of a thing with two
derivatives acting on the the metric
tensor ok the next time we will explore
what a and B are what the principles are
which govern a and B and what the
numbers I'll tell you like now the
numbers are 1 and 1/2
1 plus 1/2 1 minus 1/2 where does I ever
know
yeah so they're real easy numbers and
and all we really have to show well we
have to show a little more than that but
but that's the that's the basic set of
ideas and we that's general relativity
so not so hard is it
the preceding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu